<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mragank Shekhar</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Mragank Shekhar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mgeeeek.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>GSoC Coding period: first phase part 1</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/gsoc-coding-period-first-phase-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/gsoc-coding-period-first-phase-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Community Bonding period ended on 31st May, I covered my experience with PySAL community during the CB period in my last blog. The coding period has started at the beginning of this month and we’ve already reached midway of the first phase. Through this blog, I’ll share what all I’ve been working on during these couple of weeks.
What I did before coding period As stated in the last blog, during the community bonding period my focus was to grow my understanding of libpysal&#39;s structure, codebase, and API design paradigms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community bonding period wrap-up</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/community-bonding-period-wrap-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/community-bonding-period-wrap-up/</guid>
      <description>Today marks the end of the community bonding period and the beginning of the coding period of GSoC. In this blog, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience with the PySAL community during the community bonding period. The community bonding period is the starting phase in the GSoC timeline which lasts for almost a month. This period is specially designed for students to get introduced to the community and to understand and learn more about the project before the coding period starts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$ sudo make my summer thrilling</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</guid>
      <description>It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something, and the situation looks still the same&amp;hellip;
Coming to some good news&amp;hellip; My last blog ended with the submission of my GSoC proposal. From the framing of my sentence you would&amp;rsquo;ve guessed already that my GSoC2020 proposal got accepted. I wanted to tell you about this on the day I received my acceptance letter but this semester drained the soul out of me just like what happened to prison mike in prison.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$ blog init</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</guid>
      <description>From now on I&amp;rsquo;ll try to document all the major experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve gained involving opensource development, research work, and exciting stuff like game-theory, python-libraries, Linux-distro-kernel(this is what I come to when I&amp;rsquo;m super bored), philosophy-morality-religion(I&amp;rsquo;m being pretentious now), and most importantly trending topics in the field of AI/ML&amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s leave right here cos I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything in my mind right now except for thinking about the ongoing situation because of the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>Education BENNETT UNIVERSITY
B.Tech. in Computer Science And Engineering
2017 - 2021(expected) | Greater Noida, UP
 CGPA (till 5th semester) – 7.69/10 Relevant Coursework:Data Structures, OS, DBMS, Algorithms, OOPs with JAVA, Machine learning, Big Data, Linear Algebra, Probability and Statistics, Numerical Methods.  Publications TRAINING MULTI-LAYER PERCEPTRON USING POPULATION BASED YIN-YANG-PAIR OPTIMIZATION
 M. Shekhar, accepted and presented in The International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Applications (ICAIA’2020), to appear in the Springer proc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shortnote</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/short/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/short/</guid>
      <description>CSE 💻 undergrad who&amp;rsquo;s quite passionate about opensource development, machine learning, and 📱 android app-development. I&amp;rsquo;m always looking for new ways to optimize existing solution. My current work revolves around android app-development, recommender systems, and evolutionary computing. Apart from this I&amp;rsquo;m huge fan of thriller/sci-fi/psychological anime, movies, and souls-like 🎮 (really ❤️ them but no 🕦 to invest 😞).
Get to know me better</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>