<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mragank Shekhar</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Mragank Shekhar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mgeeeek.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>$ sudo make my summer thrilling</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</guid>
      <description>How this year turned out horrible for all students… really exciting news at the end though!!! It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something. This year is one of the most tragic and hard-hitting for all of us, I don’t want to stretch over the current situation so let&amp;rsquo;s jump straight on to my worst experience with any semester till now.
The worst thing for me, personally is the ongoing semester which is taking forever to end.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$ blog init</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</guid>
      <description>From now on I&amp;rsquo;ll try to document all the major experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve gained involving opensource development, research work, and exciting stuff like game-theory, python-libraries, Linux-distro-kernel(this is what I come to when I&amp;rsquo;m super bored), philosophy-morality-religion(I&amp;rsquo;m being pretentious now), and most importantly trending topics in the field of AI/ML&amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s leave right here cos I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything in my mind right now except for thinking about the ongoing situation because of the pandemic.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About Me</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>Education BENNETT UNIVERSITY
B.Tech. in Computer Science And Engineering
2017 - 2021(expected) | Greater Noida, UP
 CGPA (till 5th semester) – 7.69/10 Relevant Coursework:Data Structures, OS, DBMS, Algorithms, OOPs with JAVA, Machine learning, Big Data, Linear Algebra, Probability and Statistics, Numerical Methods.  Publications TRAINING MULTI-LAYER PERCEPTRON USING POPULATION BASED YIN-YANG-PAIR OPTIMIZATION
 M. Shekhar, accepted and presented in The International Conference on Artificial Intelligence and Applications (ICAIA’2020), to appear in the Springer proc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shortnote</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/short/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/short/</guid>
      <description>CSE 💻 undergrad who&amp;rsquo;s quite passionate about opensource development, machine learning, and 📱 android app-development. I&amp;rsquo;m always looking for new ways to optimize existing solution. My current work revolves around android app-development, recommender systems, and evolutionary computing. Apart from this I&amp;rsquo;m huge fan of thriller/sci-fi/psychological anime, movies, and souls-like 🎮 (really ❤️ them but no 🕦 to invest 😞).
Get to know me better</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>