<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
        <title>MgeeeeK Home</title>
        <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/</link>
        <description>About LoveIt Theme</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><managingEditor>yesthisismrshekhar@gmail.com (Mragank Shekhar)</managingEditor>
            <webMaster>yesthisismrshekhar@gmail.com (Mragank Shekhar)</webMaster><copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</lastBuildDate>
            <atom:link href="https://mgeeeek.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        <item>
    <title>Summer with Amazon and ArviZ</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/sum_with_amz_and_arviz/</link>
    <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/sum_with_amz_and_arviz/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[You might be in a hurry so TL;DR Horrible year so far, but luckily I got a chance to work at Amazon as a Data Engineer Intern and recently, my gsoc proposal got accepted so I&rsquo;ll also work with ArviZ community this summer. Now, it’s been a while since I have posted something, and therefore I&rsquo;ll let my heart speak for now&hellip;
He tried okay!! jk! will update this in the coming days.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>GSoC2020 Project Report</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/final_report/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 30 Aug 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/final_report/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Project Details    Field Value     Project Title Raster Awareness in PySAL   Project Link https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/#5775104799145984   Organization NumFOCUS (Sub-Org: PySAL)   Mentors Stefanie Lumnitz, Dani Arribas-Bel, Levi John Wolf   Contributed Repo libpysal, splot   Working Repo Mgeeeek/libpysal   Gitter Room https://gitter.im/GSoC2020-PySAL/Raster_awareness_in_PySAL   Project Blog https://mgeeeek.github.io/tags/gsoc/    Project Description From early on, PySAL was designed with the focus of performing vector-based spatial analysis and therefore it didn&rsquo;t have tools to handle input-output of large raster data.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Coding Period: Last Phase Part 1</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp31/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 17 Aug 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp31/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[We are in the end phase of GSOC now and less than 2 weeks are remaining for finishing up our project. My last blog focused on the working of base raster interface API which is in the beta phase as it is still being reviewed by other community members. Most of my time in the first half of this phase went in optimizing the weights builder and efficiently increasing the neighbors of the focal point, let&rsquo;s jump straight to the exciting stuff.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Coding Period: Second Phase Part 2</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp22/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 31 Jul 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp22/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Phase two of GSoC2020 is over, this blog is little late cos my laptop&rsquo;s HDD died and I was unable to save my Hugo environment. Overall the summer has been really productive and the API design of the interface is finally reached beta period, let&rsquo;s look at the progress.
Final API of the Interface After several weeks of coding, design discussions, and code review, phase 1 of my project which consisted of designing API and all the functionality for the base raster interface is completed.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Coding Period: Second Phase Part 1</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp21/</link>
    <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp21/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Phase 1 of the coding period has already completed and we&rsquo;ve had almost reached the midpoint of the coding period. This blog will provide a short update of the work done in the last couple of weeks.
API Status At the end of Phase 1, there were some bug fixes and API changes that my mentors suggested, these were minor changes that were quickly included in the project in the following week.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Coding Period: First Phase Part 2</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp12/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp12/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Phase 1 of the coding period is about to get over and 2 weeks have already passed since I gave an update on my GSoC project. As per my last blog, I successfully implemented the prototype transformation methods of the base interface, let’s look at the developments happened after the first 2 weeks.
Progress on the Project The main goal of the first phase was to implement and finalize the base raster interface, in other words, I had to incorporate all methods which can be utilized to make the transformations from xarray.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Coding Period: First Phase Part 1</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp11/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cdp11/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Community Bonding period ended on 31st May, I covered my experience with PySAL community during the CB period in my last blog. The coding period has started at the beginning of this month and we’ve already reached midway of the first phase. Through this blog, I’ll share what all I’ve been working on during these couple of weeks.
Overview of 2 Spatial Weight Objects During the community bonding period my focus was to grow my understanding of libpysal&rsquo;s structure, codebase, and API design paradigms.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>Community bonding period wrap-up</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cbpw/</link>
    <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/cbpw/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[Today marks the end of the community bonding period and the beginning of the coding period of GSoC. In this blog, I&rsquo;ll share my experience with the PySAL community during the community bonding period.
The community bonding period is the starting phase in the GSoC timeline which lasts for almost a month. This period is specially designed for students to get introduced to the community and to understand and learn more about the project before the coding period starts.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>$ sudo make my summer thrilling</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/sgn/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/sgn/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something, and the situation looks still the same&hellip;
Coming to some good news&hellip; My last blog ended with the submission of my GSoC proposal. From the framing of my sentence you would&rsquo;ve guessed already that my GSoC2020 proposal got accepted. I wanted to tell you about this on the day I received my acceptance letter but this semester drained the soul out of me just like what happened to prison mike in prison.]]></description>
</item><item>
    <title>$ blog init</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/first-blog/</link>
    <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 &#43;0000</pubDate>
    <author>Author</author>
    <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/first-blog/</guid>
    <description><![CDATA[From now on I&rsquo;ll try to document all the major experiences I&rsquo;ve gained involving opensource development, research work, and exciting stuff like game-theory, python-libraries, Linux-distro-kernel(this is what I come to when I&rsquo;m super bored), philosophy-morality-religion(I&rsquo;m being pretentious now), and most importantly trending topics in the field of AI/ML&hellip; let&rsquo;s leave right here cos I don&rsquo;t have anything in my mind right now except for thinking about the ongoing situation because of the pandemic.]]></description>
</item></channel>
</rss>
