<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>gsoc on Mragank Shekhar</title>
    <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/tags/gsoc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in gsoc on Mragank Shekhar</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://mgeeeek.github.io/tags/gsoc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Coding period: second phase part 1</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/07/coding-period-second-phase-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/07/coding-period-second-phase-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Phase 1 of the coding period has already completed and we&amp;rsquo;ve had almost reached the midpoint of the coding period. This blog will provide a short update of the work done in the last couple of weeks.
API Status At the end of Phase 1, there were some bug fixes and API changes that my mentors suggested, these were minor changes that were quickly included in the project in the following week.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coding period: first phase part 2</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/coding-period-first-phase-part-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/coding-period-first-phase-part-2/</guid>
      <description>Phase 1 of the coding period is about to get over and 2 weeks have already passed since I gave an update on my GSoC project. As per my last blog, I successfully implemented the prototype transformation methods of the base interface, let’s look at the developments happened after the first 2 weeks.
Progress on the Project The main goal of the first phase was to implement and finalize the base raster interface, in other words, I had to incorporate all methods which can be utilized to make the transformations from xarray.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coding period: first phase part 1</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/coding-period-first-phase-part-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/coding-period-first-phase-part-1/</guid>
      <description>Community Bonding period ended on 31st May, I covered my experience with PySAL community during the CB period in my last blog. The coding period has started at the beginning of this month and we’ve already reached midway of the first phase. Through this blog, I’ll share what all I’ve been working on during these couple of weeks.
Overview of 2 Spatial Weight Objects During the community bonding period my focus was to grow my understanding of libpysal&#39;s structure, codebase, and API design paradigms.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Community bonding period wrap-up</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/community-bonding-period-wrap-up/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/community-bonding-period-wrap-up/</guid>
      <description>Today marks the end of the community bonding period and the beginning of the coding period of GSoC. In this blog, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience with the PySAL community during the community bonding period. The community bonding period is the starting phase in the GSoC timeline which lasts for almost a month. This period is specially designed for students to get introduced to the community and to understand and learn more about the project before the coding period starts.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>$ sudo make my summer thrilling</title>
      <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</guid>
      <description>It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something, and the situation looks still the same&amp;hellip;
Coming to some good news&amp;hellip; My last blog ended with the submission of my GSoC proposal. From the framing of my sentence you would&amp;rsquo;ve guessed already that my GSoC2020 proposal got accepted. I wanted to tell you about this on the day I received my acceptance letter but this semester drained the soul out of me just like what happened to prison mike in prison.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>