<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Mragank Shekhar</title>
        <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Mragank Shekhar</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>$ sudo make my summer thrilling</title>
            <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</guid>
            <description>It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something, and the situation looks still the same&amp;hellip;
Coming to some good news&amp;hellip; My last blog ended with the submission of my GSoC proposal. From the framing of my sentence you would&amp;rsquo;ve guessed already that my GSoC2020 proposal got accepted. I wanted to tell you about this on the day I received my acceptance letter but this semester drained the soul out of me just like what happened to prison mike in prison.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something, and the situation looks still the same&hellip;</p>
<p>Coming to some good news&hellip; My last blog ended with the submission of my GSoC proposal. From the framing of my sentence you would&rsquo;ve guessed already that my GSoC2020 proposal got accepted. I wanted to tell you about this on the day I received my acceptance letter but this semester drained the soul out of me just like what happened to prison mike in prison. But on the serious note, I&rsquo;ll work under NumFOCUS which is an umbrella organization supporting relatively small organizations related to scientific computing. The organization I&rsquo;ve chosen under NumFOCUS is PySAL (an abbreviation of Python Spatial Analysis Library) mainly used in geospatial data science. My project <strong><em>Raster awareness in PySAL</em></strong> proposes an interface that will support PySAL’s statistical operations on raster objects (more details can be obtained from the <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/5775104799145984">abstract</a>). The project focuses more on the core part of the library and connects with other analytical and statistical components of PySAL, which makes it really interesting and therefore I’m super excited to work on it this summer.</p>
<p>Time for me to take the leave. I hope this situation gets over as soon as possible&hellip; till then goodbye, lock yourself at home and stay safe, more importantly, wait for my next blog which will be related to my initial work on the project.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>$ blog init</title>
            <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</guid>
            <description>From now on I&amp;rsquo;ll try to document all the major experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve gained involving opensource development, research work, and exciting stuff like game-theory, python-libraries, Linux-distro-kernel(this is what I come to when I&amp;rsquo;m super bored), philosophy-morality-religion(I&amp;rsquo;m being pretentious now), and most importantly trending topics in the field of AI/ML&amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s leave right here cos I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything in my mind right now except for thinking about the ongoing situation because of the pandemic.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From now on I&rsquo;ll <strong>try</strong> to document all the major experiences I&rsquo;ve gained involving opensource development, research work, and exciting stuff like game-theory, python-libraries, Linux-distro-kernel(this is what I come to when I&rsquo;m super bored), philosophy-morality-religion(I&rsquo;m being pretentious now), and most importantly trending topics in the field of AI/ML&hellip; let&rsquo;s leave right here cos I don&rsquo;t have anything in my mind right now except for thinking about the ongoing situation because of the pandemic. I&rsquo;ll also submit my GSoC proposal today (hopefully I&rsquo;ll get selected&hellip; oh boy!! super excited for this summer). Till then goodbye, lock yourself at home&hellip; and stay safe.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
