<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Posts on Mragank Shekhar</title>
        <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/</link>
        <description>Recent content in Posts on Mragank Shekhar</description>
        <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
        <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</copyright>
        <lastBuildDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
        <atom:link href="https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Coding period phase 1 part 1</title>
            <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/coding-period-phase-1-part-1/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/06/coding-period-phase-1-part-1/</guid>
            <description>Community Bonding period ended on 31st May, I covered my experience with PySAL community during the CB period in my last blog. The coding period has started at the beginning of this month and we’ve already reached midway of the first phase. Through this blog, I’ll share what all I’ve been working on during these couple of weeks.
What I did before coding period As stated in the last blog, during the community bonding period my focus was to grow my understanding of libpysal&#39;s structure, codebase, and API design paradigms.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Community Bonding period ended on 31st May, I covered my experience with PySAL community during the CB period in my last blog. The coding period has started at the beginning of this month and we’ve already reached midway of the first phase. Through this blog, I’ll share what all I’ve been working on during these couple of weeks.</em></p>
<h2 id="what-i-did-before-coding-period">What I did before coding period</h2>
<p>As stated in the last blog, during the community bonding period my focus was to grow my understanding of <code>libpysal</code>'s structure, codebase, and API design paradigms. Along with this, I was looking deeply at the 2 types of spatial class objects used in PySAL namely <code>W</code> &amp; <code>WSP</code> objects which are used to construct spatial weight matrices, specifically I was understanding the logic and structure of each object and ways in which both of them are created. Lemme provides a bit overview of each object (this is a fairly basic explanation, please refer to this <a href="https://youtu.be/fc1f4MNLzdQ?t=5424">video</a> or the main <a href="https://pysal.org/libpysal/">documentation</a> of <code>libpysal</code>).</p>
<p><strong>Spatial Weights Matrix</strong>: In general, it expresses the relationship of a spatial point with its neighboring points. It can be viewed as an adjacency matrix of a weighted graph where each node is connected to other node and these connections follow a specific spatial-contiguity like rook or queen (there are other contiguities as well but these 2 are intuitive to understand).</p>
<p><strong><code>W object</code></strong>: Also known as dense weight object, it is used to construct spatial weight and represent it in the form of 2 dictionaries-</p>
<ul>
<li><code>neighbor dictionary</code>, where each key specifies a selected point, and the corresponding value is a list containing neighbors of the selected point.</li>
<li><code>weight dictionary</code>, similar to the neighbor dictionary but instead of specifying neighbors, the list contains the weight of each connection of the key to the neighbor listed in the neighbor dictionary.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong><code>WSP object</code></strong>: It is also used to construct spatial weight but unlike <code>W</code> object it represents the spatial weights in the form of a sparse matrix where each row shows the relationship of a point with every other point.</p>
<p>Constructing a <code>WSP</code> object requires fewer computations when compared to constructing a <code>W</code> object, but it does not contain the same amount of information as a <code>W</code> object. PySAL&rsquo;s statistical methods operate on these two objects and until now these two objects are mainly derived from vector data (which can be presented in the form of different structures like data frame, shapefiles).</p>
<h2 id="what-did-i-do-this-week">What did I do this week?</h2>
<p>Coming back to the coding period, in my project proposal I listed out the following tasks to be done in the first 2 weeks.</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Week 1 &amp; 2</em> (1st June - 14th June) :</p>
<ul>
<li>List out initial functionalities to be incorporated in the interface.</li>
<li>Implement necessary methods for streamlining the access to raster data using <code>rasterio</code> inside PySAL.</li>
<li>Add methods to extract extract metadata from rasters.</li>
<li>Create an optimized functionality for handling missing values in the raster data used by prototype transformational methods.</li>
<li>Investigate inner working of <code>georasters</code> methods, since some of its functionality can be improved and used for this project.</li>
<li>Discuss the proposed design of the API of interface and this will be worked upon in the next week.</li>
</ul>
</blockquote>
<p>During the CBP I&rsquo;d several discussions with my mentors and it was decided that <code>xarray</code> will be used for the project instead of <code>rasterio</code> because <code>xarray</code> provides a proper structure to the raster&rsquo;s metadata which makes it easy for a user to manipulate and access properties of raster file using <code>xarray.DataArray</code> object.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I had my exams going on during the first week of the coding period, therefore I was a little unproductive and could not completely focus on the project. During this time I set up my development environment, looked at <code>georasters</code> library, and worked on how I can convert <code>xarray.DataArray</code> to weight object.</p>
<p>Since my exams were over by next week I was able to devote my time to the project. My main task this week was to work on prototype transformational methods that can be used in transforming the raster file accessed using <code>xarray</code> to <code>W</code> and <code>SW</code> objects. Along with this I also worked on converting results back to <code>xarray.Dataframe</code> object.</p>
<p>PR made during this period:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MgeeeeK/libpysal/pull/1">Added rast2(W,SW)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://github.com/MgeeeeK/libpysal/pull/2">Added func for creating xr.dataarray</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Since I used the <code>lat2W</code> method, I noticed that the <code>W</code> object stores the neighbors in the list and for large values of rows and columns (2 arguments of the function) the computation runs out of memory, this problem will exist since the methods use eager evaluation. I plan to create an additional method which computes the dictionary values of <code>W</code> object lazily, working with generator objects is tough in this situation since some of the PySAL&rsquo;s methods require all data of <code>W</code> object in memory. This requires more time and I will see if it can be modified in a way so that the PySAL library can work with it.</p>
<h2 id="whats-next">What&rsquo;s next?</h2>
<p>During my recent project call, both mentors reviewed my work and suggested some corrections in the API and the function implementation. In the coming weeks, I have to incorporate the suggested changes and finalize both transformational methods (their APIs and return objects) and also work on the optimization part.</p>
<p>Wait for my next blog which will show the working of my contributed methods&hellip; Till then goodbye 👋.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Community bonding period wrap-up</title>
            <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/community-bonding-period-wrap-up/</link>
            <pubDate>Sun, 31 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/community-bonding-period-wrap-up/</guid>
            <description>Today marks the end of the community bonding period and the beginning of the coding period of GSoC. In this blog, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my experience with the PySAL community during the community bonding period. The community bonding period is the starting phase in the GSoC timeline which lasts for almost a month. This period is specially designed for students to get introduced to the community and to understand and learn more about the project before the coding period starts.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="today-marks-the-end-of-the-community-bonding-period-and-the-beginning-of-the-coding-period-of-gsoc-in-this-blog-ill-share-my-experience-with-the-pysal-community-during-the-community-bonding-period">Today marks the end of the community bonding period and the beginning of the coding period of GSoC. In this blog, I&rsquo;ll share my experience with the PySAL community during the community bonding period.</h3>
<p>The community bonding period is the starting phase in the GSoC timeline which lasts for almost a month. This period is specially designed for students to get introduced to the community and to understand and learn more about the project before the coding period starts. Additionally, students are also expected to become familiar with documentations, open-source practices, and procedures.</p>
<p>Most of my time during the community bonding period was devoted to studying the <code>libpysal</code>'s codebase thoroughly to comprehend its structure, internal functions and testing procedures, I also worked on the examples and read documentation of <code>rasterio</code> and <code>xarray</code> to understand these libraries in depth. Because of my semester getting extended by one month I was not able to dedicate more time to the project as planned earlier in my proposal, I tried to wrap up my coursework, assignments and end-sem exam preparation so that I can completely focus on the project in the coming week.</p>
<h3 id="meetings-and-progress">Meetings and Progress</h3>
<p>In total 3 projects were selected by the PySAL community for this summer. To keep the project-related meetings and interaction more efficient and productive, it was decided by the mentors to coordinate every other week with all gsoc project members and separately in the off-weeks with individual project members. During the community bonding period 3 meetings/calls occurred, one call every Friday.</p>
<ul>
<li>The first call was an introductory meeting involving all students and mentors from each project. This meeting was more about getting to know each other, everyone introduced themselves and also discussed about current state of PySAL and how community use it in their research work. Additionally, we talked about git conventions and setting up the development environment using anaconda. The first meeting was really fruitful and everyone was very friendly and welcoming.</li>
</ul>
<p>Before the next meeting, my project mentors Dani and Stefanie provided me with some additional resources related to the project. Since I&rsquo;m very new in the field of geospatial data science and GIS, I’ve been heavily involved with reading a lot of documentation and learning new things which will help me to get familiar with different statistical methods in PySAL and how they use different data structure as input.</p>
<ul>
<li>The project-specific meeting which happened one week after the first meeting only involved the mentors and student working on that project, mine was related to my project which is Raster awareness in PySAL. I updated the mentors with my proposed approach provided in the proposal, discussed the roadmap for integrating the interface to the library and talked about possible changes in the proposal, it was also cleared by the mentors that the interface with minimal changes in the core computational structure takes priority over making use of Dask since this might require a lot of research and time. The rest of our discussion was related to possible features and functionality to be included after the completion of phase 1. We also discussed about project progress tracking/management and later decided to use issue and PRs with project tag as project tracking diary.</li>
</ul>
<p>Since I&rsquo;d my exams during this week, I was not able to contribute/submit any patch related to the project. Instead, I worked and explored an efficient way to transform <code>xarray.dataArray</code> object to PySAL weight object as discussed during the last meeting. I noticed that while using the <code>Lat2W</code> function I was able to transform correctly, but building a weight object using <code>Lat2W</code> with large values of rows and columns resulted in memory overflow as it uses lists for storing the neighbors, weights, and ids in the dictionary. I&rsquo;m planning to explore this in-depth next week and push a patch related to this.</p>
<ul>
<li>In the last meeting of the community bonding period, mentors cleared some doubts which students had and discussed possible ways of project tracking and management. I also had a call with my project mentors to discuss deliverables I&rsquo;m supposed to work on during the first week of the coding period.</li>
</ul>
<p>With my exams finishing up in the mid of next week, I am looking forward to having a really productive and wonderful summer ahead, learning and contributing exciting stuff to PySAL. Till then, adios !!</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>$ sudo make my summer thrilling</title>
            <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/05/sudo-make-my-summer-thrilling/</guid>
            <description>It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something, and the situation looks still the same&amp;hellip;
Coming to some good news&amp;hellip; My last blog ended with the submission of my GSoC proposal. From the framing of my sentence you would&amp;rsquo;ve guessed already that my GSoC2020 proposal got accepted. I wanted to tell you about this on the day I received my acceptance letter but this semester drained the soul out of me just like what happened to prison mike in prison.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It’s been a while since I posted or blogged about something, and the situation looks still the same&hellip;</p>
<p>Coming to some good news&hellip; My last blog ended with the submission of my GSoC proposal. From the framing of my sentence you would&rsquo;ve guessed already that my GSoC2020 proposal got accepted. I wanted to tell you about this on the day I received my acceptance letter but this semester drained the soul out of me just like what happened to prison mike in prison. But on the serious note, I&rsquo;ll work under NumFOCUS which is an umbrella organization supporting relatively small organizations related to scientific computing. The organization I&rsquo;ve chosen under NumFOCUS is PySAL (an abbreviation of Python Spatial Analysis Library) mainly used in geospatial data science. My project <strong><em>Raster awareness in PySAL</em></strong> proposes an interface that will support PySAL’s statistical operations on raster objects (more details can be obtained from the <a href="https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/projects/5775104799145984">abstract</a>). The project focuses more on the core part of the library and connects with other analytical and statistical components of PySAL, which makes it really interesting and therefore I’m super excited to work on it this summer.</p>
<p>Time for me to take the leave. I hope this situation gets over as soon as possible&hellip; till then goodbye, lock yourself at home and stay safe, more importantly, wait for my next blog which will be related to my initial work on the project.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>$ blog init</title>
            <link>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</link>
            <pubDate>Mon, 30 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
            
            <guid>https://mgeeeek.github.io/posts/2020/03/blog-init/</guid>
            <description>From now on I&amp;rsquo;ll try to document all the major experiences I&amp;rsquo;ve gained involving opensource development, research work, and exciting stuff like game-theory, python-libraries, Linux-distro-kernel(this is what I come to when I&amp;rsquo;m super bored), philosophy-morality-religion(I&amp;rsquo;m being pretentious now), and most importantly trending topics in the field of AI/ML&amp;hellip; let&amp;rsquo;s leave right here cos I don&amp;rsquo;t have anything in my mind right now except for thinking about the ongoing situation because of the pandemic.</description>
            <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>From now on I&rsquo;ll <strong>try</strong> to document all the major experiences I&rsquo;ve gained involving opensource development, research work, and exciting stuff like game-theory, python-libraries, Linux-distro-kernel(this is what I come to when I&rsquo;m super bored), philosophy-morality-religion(I&rsquo;m being pretentious now), and most importantly trending topics in the field of AI/ML&hellip; let&rsquo;s leave right here cos I don&rsquo;t have anything in my mind right now except for thinking about the ongoing situation because of the pandemic. I&rsquo;ll also submit my GSoC proposal today (hopefully I&rsquo;ll get selected&hellip; oh boy!! super excited for this summer). Till then goodbye, lock yourself at home&hellip; and stay safe.</p>
]]></content>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
